<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The honour of the gout: or, A rational discourse, demonstrating that the gout is one of the greatest blessings which can befal mortal man that all gentlemen who are weary of it, are their own enemies; that those pratitioners who offer at the cure, are the vainest and most mischievous cheats in nature. By way of letter to an eminent citizen, wrote in the heat of a violent paroxysm, and now published for the common good. By Philander Misiatus.</title>
            <author>Philander Misaurus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44298</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2598</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215301</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827213</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827213</idno>
            <idno type="VID">31629</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44298)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31629)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1888:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The honour of the gout: or, A rational discourse, demonstrating that the gout is one of the greatest blessings which can befal mortal man that all gentlemen who are weary of it, are their own enemies; that those pratitioners who offer at the cure, are the vainest and most mischievous cheats in nature. By way of letter to an eminent citizen, wrote in the heat of a violent paroxysm, and now published for the common good. By Philander Misiatus.</title>
                  <author>Philander Misaurus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 61, [7] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for A. Baldwin, in Warwick-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M DC XC IX. [1699]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Philander Misiatrus is a pseudonym.</note>
                  <note>"To all the numerous offspring of Apollo, whether dogmatical sons of art, or empirical by-blows" has caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gout --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:31629:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HONOUR OF THE GOUT:</p>
            <p>OR, A Rational Diſcourſe, demonſtrating that the Gout is one of the greateſt Bleſſings which can befal Mortal Man; that all Gentlemen who are weary of it, are their own Enemies; that thoſe Practitioners who offer at the Cure, are the vaineſt and moſt miſchievous Cheats in Nature.</p>
            <p>By way of Letter to an Eminent Citizen, Wrote in the heat of a violent Paroxyſm, and now Publiſhed for the Common Good.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Philander Miſiatrus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>A. Baldwin,</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane.</hi> MDCXCIX.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:31629:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31629:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:31629:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31629:3"/>
            <head>THE PUBLISHER TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THis Piece, which I preſent you, [as appears from many Paſſages in it,] was Wrote towards the beginning of the Reign of King <hi>William;</hi> whether or no the Author be living, I cannot ſatisfie you; but this I will engage, greater Profit, and more agreeable Entertainment were never pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed, of a Bookſeller Cheaper.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:31629:4"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THE Author is of Opinion, That ſome Epiſtles Dedicatory would do beſt ſtanding af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Pamphlet, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, good Reader, paſs on, and expect mine in its proper place.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:31629:4"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Owe you a greater Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, more profound Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, and hearty Thanks, for Favours to which I had not Merit to pretend, than I am able to expreſs, ſhould I make Words and Phraſe my Study; but I am not like to do that at preſent; for you have us'd me ſo of late, that you tempt me to think, you are going to put as much Deſpight into one Scale, as ever you put Obligation into the other. Why! Sir, I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, that your Worſhip, not having a right ſenſe of things, nor the Fear of God before your Eyes, ſhould, to the diſgrace of your own Vertue, give your Tongue the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, in an open Coffee-Houſe, to ſpeak ill of the Gout. Of the Gout, Sir! which if you look on as a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, you ought to welcome as the moſt uſeful and neceſſary thing,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:31629:5"/>that could have happen'd to you: But if you conſider as becomes you, then, with me, you muſt reverence it as a Power Divine,
<q>
                  <l>On whoſe Sacred internodial Altars, I</l>
                  <l>Each Spring and Fall, at leaſt, will ſacrifice,</l>
                  <l>Morbiſick painful loads of Matter tartarous,</l>
                  <l>With Recrements of nervous juice impregnate.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Would you your ſelf, Sir, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently endure the Honour of our Great Maſter, our Rightful and Lawful King, to be contemptuouſly reflected on, by e're a recreant piece of Conſcientious Prieſt-craft that infeſts the Town? Then, why ſhould not I be concerned for the Honour of my Great Maſter, the Gout, who claims not, 'tis true, the power he exerciſes over me, by any Hereditary pretence; but from an Origine altogether as Sacred and Indiſputable, <hi>viz.</hi> ſome voluntary Acts and Deeds of my own. Yet you could ſay, that when the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God had out of rude <hi>Chaos</hi> built this goodly frame of Nature, which we ſee, and form'd his Noble
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:31629:5"/>Creature Man; he indulged the Devil to Create ſome one thing, and his damn'd Envy gave Being to the Gout. Now I am confident, Sir, and have great Authorities for it, that if the Devil ever created any thing, it was the Doctor, of whom ſince you have made ſo much uſe; I know not, but it may be rationally inferr'd, that you have dealt with the Devil. The Gout, Sir, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you know it or no, was poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to the Creation, and younger ſomething than the Fall of Man, who having incurr'd the Sentence of Death, the friendly Gout was ſent in Mercy down from Heaven to lengthen waſting Life: By my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you ſhould never have the Gout, who have no more conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in you than to blaſpheme it.</p>
            <p>I always took your Worſhip for a Perſon the moſt accommpliſhed our City has ever bred; I imagin'd that you thoroughly underſtood moſt things, but it could never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into my head, that you ſhould fall into ſo Profane an Errour as to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:31629:6"/>think, into ſo raſh a Practice, as to ſpeak ill of the Gout. But becauſe my Soul has been full of humble Deference to your Worſhip, I will be at ſome pains to recover you to your right mind, and a due venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Friendly Daemon, the Gout. For though you may value your ſelf, and reckon that no gird<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Satyriſt can take up the Old Proverb againſt you, and ſay, That you are afraid of your Friends, when there is none near you; yet, what is worſe, they may reproach you with this diſgraceful Truth; You are afraid of your beſt Friend when he Kiſſes your very feet.</p>
            <p>Now upon this Subject, having no need to uſe the inveagling Arts of Oratory; I ſhall not with Tropes and Metaphors, with Flouriſhes and Amuſements of inſinuating Words, ſeek to divert your Mind, and cheat your Judgment; but to make my Work the ſhorter, and do it ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually, preſs you with plain De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration. Your Errour, Sir, was this, That the Devil Created
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:31629:6"/>the Gout. I prove he did not. You know, Sir, that the Man of Sin, the Son of Perdition, beſt known by the Name of Antichriſt, is the Pope. You muſt not doubt of this, for till the days of that Excellent Prelate, Archbiſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> the whole ſtream of Proteſtant In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters gave it ſo; a learned Chaplain of his has put that Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter upon the Grand Seignior, and a famous Annotator has taught our Church to ſplit Antichriſt into <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> and his Gnoſtick Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers. I muſt confeſs, I have a ſort of a reſpect to theſe Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but the Body of Modern Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, and the general Agreement of Interpreters, Whig and Tory, in the Age before, weighs them down: Take in then the Lay-mobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Nation, who ſhould know ſomething, but are confident of nothing more, than that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt is the Pope; and your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip will agree it with me, that that's the plain Truth of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: By the way I will obſerve one
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:31629:7"/>thing, which will not trouble my Demonſtration, but yet your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſee, how ready I am to allow you in your Speculation, all that can reaſonably be deſir'd. A cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated Author notes, that the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients deſcribed Antichriſt, by the Phraſe of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The Firſt-Born of the Devil. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing now that the Devil created ſomething, as you contend, you ſee, it could not be the Gout; at leaſt, not if you'll be judged by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; but rather Antichriſt, or the Pope. I deſire your Worſhip to conſider next, that you ſhall not read in <hi>Platina, Onuphrius,</hi> or any latter Antichriſtian Biographer, that ever faetid Toe of Pope was viſited with beneficial Gout. But had ſo great a Bleſſing been created by the Devil, as you fondly imagine, the Devil had for a certain, beſtow'd it on his Firſt-born the Pope: Nay, and then too, inſtead of the filthy Scrutiny through the Porphiry Chair, for old and waſted Teſticles, the Deacon had only pull'd off the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:31629:7"/>Stocking of the Elect, and the rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatory Report had been, <hi>Dominus noster Papa habet Podagram.</hi> In ſhort, Sir, Antichriſt, or the Pope, [for they are one and the ſame Firſt-born of the Devil, according to the Ancients,] being never favoured with the Gout, it is plain that the Devil did not create it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which was the thing to be demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated.</p>
            <p>Having thus, Sir, utterly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded your Errour, my next la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſhall be, to inſtruct you in a ſounder perſuaſion. The Gout was ſent in Mercy down from Heaven to lengthen waſting Life.</p>
            <p>The Seat of this Friendly Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, by whom every afflicted Man receives a thouſand times more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, than ever <hi>Socrates,</hi> by his; his Seat, I ſay, is in the Nervous parts; he commonly viſits the <hi>Internodia</hi> of the Bones of the Feet; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Hip, the Knee, the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow, Shoulder, Wriſt, and Ancle: But to prove its Divine Original, I will proceed methodically, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:31629:8"/>from his loweſt Commendations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend by ſix juſt Steps or Degrees, till I have rais'd him above the Stars, and enter'd him among the Celeſtial Spirits; to whom, Sir, you will then be tempted to offer up your Oraiſons in the preſcribed Form, at the end of an Old Manuſcript-Miſſal, communicated to me by a learned Antiquary, a great Collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of thoſe Rarities. The Form this; Bleſſed Gout, moſt deſirable Gout, Soveraign Antidote of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Maladies, powerful Correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of Intemperance, deign to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit me with thy purging fires, and throw off the tophous injury which I may have ſuffered by Wine and Wit, too hard for the Vertue of a Devote upon a Holy Feſtival; but fail not thy Humble Supplicant, who needs thy Friendly Help to keep his tottering Tenement in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, fail him not, every Vernal and Autumnal Aequinox.</p>
            <p>I know ſome preciſe Doctors are againſt all Invocation of Saints, at preſent I ſhall not diſpute with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:31629:8"/>them, but they muſt grant me, That there's more to be ſaid in juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch a Prayer to the Gout, than can be ſaid for the Offices di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to any other Saints, not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting the Virgin. For I defier their Worſhippers to prove, that there has been the Tythe of ſo much good done by them all, as I ſhall prove has been done by the beneficial Gout. I begin at the loweſt ſtep, and Note,</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>The Gout gives a Man Pain without Danger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is poſſible, I confeſs, that a Sick Man, if he were directly ask'd to declare his Senſe of the matter, might refuſe to acknowledge the benefit of <hi>Pain without Danger,</hi> for Sickneſs and Peeviſhneſs commonly go together; but mind his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe at another time, when he talks from the heart, and is not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Guard: Then, O then, <hi>Pain without Danger is a Bleſſed thing.</hi> For Inſtance, — Suffering under
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:31629:9"/>a painful threatning Diſtemper, What's his firſt queſtion to the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, but this? Doctor, pray be plain with me, and let me truly know what I am to expect, don't flatter a Sick-man, but tell me, am I like to Recover or no? That Pain, you ſee, which he ſuffers, does not at all trouble him, he's only afraid he ſhall Die, ſecure him againſt that Danger, and all is well with him: Cut, Slaſh, Burn, no pain is grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, if it promiſe to ſet us out of the danger of Death.</p>
            <p>When the other Doctor comes, the Phyſician of the Soul I mean, whoſe coming bodes no good to the Body, He tells the Decumbent a long Story of the Pains and Miſery of Life, in order to make his <hi>nunc dimittis</hi> go down the eaſier; but that method ſeldom takes, for not one of a hundred is ſo bad, but he's content to live, and put the reſt to the venture. The fear of Death is generally more grievous than all the cruel Pains of a wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:31629:9"/>Life. But ſince we muſt have pain while we live, give me the Pain of the Gout, which has no danger attending. Here ſome male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volent Adverſary may importune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly object, Did never any Man Die of the Gout? To this I anſwer, 1ſt. I have not yet affirmed, That the Gout can make a Man immortal, though I will boldly ſay thus much, it very often keeps a Man alive till all his Friends are weary of him. But 2. Should I venture to ſay that the Gout has in it ſelf the power to make a Man immortal; it ought not to ſeem ſo very ſtrange, all things being conſidered. If that be true, which ſome Authors Write of the Noble <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> He had the Secret to make a Man immortal, and I would not ſay he lyed, though himſelf Died about Forty; for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps he did not like his Company; but it muſt have been by way of his Diſcovery to give any Man the Gout when he pleaſed; in that I am poſitive. Here the Objector will
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:31629:10"/>ſcornfully put me in Mind, that Gouty perſons, ſcape Death no more than other Men, which is very true, but that's becauſe Men are Fools, and don't know when they are ſafe; they muſt be curing the Gout forſooth, and to that end they deal with the Doctor, <hi>i. e.</hi> with the Factor of Death, the Emiſſary of Hell, the Purveyor of the Grave, Damn'd Alchymiſt, good at calci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning nothing but Living Bodies in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Duſt and Aſhes. Let every one bear his own burthen; the Gout has nothing to do with the Carnage of the Doctor. All that can be ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſaid againſt the Gout, is, that it does not actually preſerve Man, in ſpight of their own Folly, and the Dr's ignorance: And yet there is the Right Honourable Sir <hi>R. H.</hi> the Gout is ſo Salutary to him that two <hi>Swiſs</hi> Doctors can't diſpatch him; what would a certain Lord give that thoſe two coagulating Spirits could remove his Honours Gout; but ſay I, <hi>Gout hold thy
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:31629:10"/>own;</hi> for Earth has more need of the Cripple, than Heaven of the Saint. And now, Sir, let me tell you a Story, the famous <hi>Willis</hi> ſhall be my Voucher, who diſſected the the Body of the Reverend, Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and Pious Doctor <hi>Hammond,</hi> kill'd purely by his Friend, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily taught him a Medicine to cure the Gout, upon the Succeſs of that Medicine, the Doctor's old Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phritic Pains return'd, and in a Fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night diſpatch'd him.</p>
            <p>Therefore for your own, for your Lady's, and for your Childrens ſake, Sir, welcome the Gout to your Houſe, and ſhut all your Doors againſt the Phyſician, I'll warrant you for up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a Hundred. Lord! how glad ſhall I be, to ſee 'em pick Chalk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones out of your Worſhip's Feet, ſome forty or fifty Years hence; by that time you'll have learn'd ſo much Patience, as never to rear for the Matter. But if you do roar [for that may be then as you uſe your ſelf now,] they that look on, if
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:31629:11"/>they love Life, will envy, not pity You: Indeed you are already a fit Object for the Envy of Thinking Men, for I have heard you confeſs, that yours is an Hereditary Gout, and that's for the better; an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary Gout is a far greater Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs than an acquir'd one; what a deal of Intemperance, and amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Exceſſes, might it have coſt Your Worſhip to have got the Gout before Forty, whereas now you have the mighty Bleſſing for nothing, <hi>ſorte naſcendi,</hi> it is your Birth-right, Sir, never think of parting with it.</p>
            <p>Perhaps you may be now tempted to ask me, how I acquir'd my Gout? I ſhall not be ſhy to ſatisfy your Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, for I came by it honeſtly: We Scholars have a way by our ſelves to come at the Bleſſing, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ever being beholden to the God, that chears the genteel Candidate of the Gout by day, or the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſs that entertains him on nights; We lead Sedentary Lives, Feed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:31629:11"/>heartily, Drink <hi>quantum ſufficit,</hi> but Sleep immoderately; ſo that, the Superfluities of our Sober and Grave Fulneſs, not exhaling, we very honeſtly prepare Tartarous Matter for the Gout, for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial Gout, which gives us Pain without Danger. Aſcend we now the next ſtep, which advances the Honour of the Gout.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Gout is no conſtant Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, but allows his Patients lucid Joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Intervals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Humane Nature is ſo fram'd, that no one thing is agreeable to it always; therefore it is well for us, that the World is ſo full of changes; the Earth we tread on, the Seas we ſail on, the Air we breath in, the Starry Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament expanded round us, have their continual Viciſſitudes, which all make for our Advantage and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light. The Body of Man is a true Microcoſm in this reſpect, for it never continues in one condition; and, upon the ſame account, his Mind is a very fit Gueſt for his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:31629:12"/>for, at different times, he thinks, and ſpeaks, different things,
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>—Modo Reges at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Tetrachas.</l>
                     <l>Omnia magna loquens, modo ſit mihi.—</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Sometimes he'd talk, of Heroes, and of Kings</l>
                     <l>In mighty ſwelling Numbers, mighty things;</l>
                     <l>And then, again, let Gracious Fortune give</l>
                     <l>A little Meat and Drink enough to live;</l>
                     <l>Let her a Coat to keep out Cold preſent,</l>
                     <l>Altho' 'tis thick, and courſe, he'll be content.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <bibl>Mr. Creech.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>How welcome is a Gueſt that knows when to be gone; but if his ſtay be longer than ordinary, we are ready to thruſt him out of doors. For theſe, and the like conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the way of the Gout's dealing with his Patients can never be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough eſteem'd. Whatever ſome impatient weak Minds may think, 'tis manifeſt, that the Gout, by his coming and going, takes the right courſe to be very agreeable, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging. Weak People may curſe the Gout, and wiſh to be wholly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd from his intermitting Viſits;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:31629:12"/>but I look upon ſuch People as Men that are weary of the World, and being willing to leave it, I grant, they have reaſon to be angry with the Gout; with the Gout that folds their Mortality ſo faſt about them.</p>
            <p>Your Worſhip has been guilty of this impatience, but I hope to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you to a better Mind. I have already ſhown you, that, to a wiſe Conſiderer, the abſence of danger takes off from the pain of the Gout, but ſome pain there is, and ought to be, for conſtant Health has no reliſh, 'tis an inſipid dull thing: That Reverend <hi>Calviniſt,</hi> Dr. <hi>Twiſs,</hi> affirms, That 'tis better to be Damn'd than Annihilated. I might, I ſuppoſe, with leſs offence, affirm, that 'twere better to be Dead, than never to be Sick of the Gout; nay, this I am ſure of, that all the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and Experienc'd People will be ſo far from taking offence, that I ſhall have them on my ſide, if I ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture on that Paradox; for, how of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten have I heard a Grave Adviſer,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:31629:13"/>one that had tried Health and Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, alternately, for many Years, tell the robuſt, young, riotous Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that he knew not the value of Health. No, how ſhould he, having never been Sick? But why ſhould his ſober Adviſer preſs him to be careful of his Health, that's the way never to underſtand the deliciouſneſs of it, by that time he gets the Gout, he'll throughly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the matter, I'll warrant him? Set me two Men together, one that never knew Pain, and another newly recover'd of the Gout; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them both narrowly, in the former perhaps you may perceive an eaſie, even Temper; but the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is raviſh'd with Joys and Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions, which, if his Tongue does not declare, his Hands, and Feet, and Geſture ſhall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Homer</hi> ſays that the Beauty of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> was a Prize, worth all the Blood ſpilt through the long courſe of the Ten Years War. <hi>Homer</hi> would not have redeem'd thoſe Lives by the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:31629:13"/>leaſt injury to that adorable Lady: Such are the lucid intervals between Heart-breaking Fits of the Gout, worth all the Ravings, and Roarings, which the violent Paroxyſm forces from the tortur'd Patient; and who would ſpoil the reſin'd Pleaſure of his Recovery, by wiſhing to have one angry Throb, one heavy Groan 'bated him. <hi>Si parvis componere mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na liceret,</hi> if we might compare great things with ſmall, The Gout is to Health, as Ham, and Tongue, to Wine, or rather, as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to the Lovers Congreſs. Courage, Sir, and be advis'd by me, 'tis good adviſe I am giving, and you ſhall have it <hi>Gratis.</hi> When your Foot ſwells, and burns, and throbs, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh all fooliſh Sorrow, and Repi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, inſtead whereof, let ſwelling Joys dilate your Generous Breaſt; when ſharp fermenting Juyces, not eaſily miſcible, ſhall meet, and by their furious conteſt, cauſe cruel twichings of your nervous Fibres, comfort your Heart, and be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:31629:14"/>pleas'd; when Maſculine Acetous Recrements ſhall, with Female Tartarous Matter, Mix, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gender, and Beget a Tophous Maſs, when that ſame Tophous Maſs ſhall lodge in the <hi>Intornodia</hi> of Your Worſhip's Bones, entertaining you with a rending Solution of Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity, then let your Soul Triumph; but touch not, taſte not, the <hi>Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men-Emulgent</hi> Doctor's Emulſions, Juleps, Apozemes, nor let his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>percuſſives, or Reſolvents, Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaſme, and Anodynes, touch you; ſo let your Friend the Gout take his courſe, and maul you ſoundly. O! ſo eaſie, ſo pleas'd, ſo joyous, ſo happy, ſo bleſs'd will you be, when the turn of Health ſhall come, why, Sir, you'll be in Heav'n, in Heav'n while you are on Earth; you'll be entirely Beatifi'd on this ſide the Grave, and that's more than <hi>Solomon</hi> has arriv'd at yet [if you can give any credit to a Catholick Painter] for but one half of him is Glorified, the other fryes in Flames,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:31629:14"/>vex'd by tormenting Devils, like the Noble <hi>Shaftsbury</hi> in <hi>Windſor-hall,</hi> beſhrew the Painter for—his Pains, <hi>Fas eſt &amp; ab hoſte doceri.</hi> Learn of our common Enemy; Sir, I fancy, the Late Tyrant ſolaces his Exile, with the expectation of a return to trample on the Liberties, and riot in the Blood of <hi>Hereticks;</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ever that diſmal day come, may the Gout, my Life's kind Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver, and my dear Life it ſelf for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake me; only I will make it in my bargain, I will not ſtand to this wiſh, if my help can contribute any thing to oppoſe his Invaſion. I am much of the Mind, Sir, that by what I have ſaid already, you are a coming Proſelyte; but before I have done with you, you ſhall chuſe to part with your Eyes, rather than your true Friend the Gout. The migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Bleſſing whereof, that you may the better underſtand, mount with me one Step higher, and then take notice of this farther advantage of the Gout.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:31629:15"/>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The Gout preſents you with a perpetual Almanack;</hi> And that it may never be out of the way, but ready always for Your Worſhip's uſe, ſafely depoſites it in the <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodia</hi> of your Bones. <hi>Barometers, Thermometers,</hi> and other the Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Men, not yet perfect Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of their Art, ſerve more for the Delight, than the Uſe of the Curious; but theuſeſul Pains of the Gout give Your Honour truſty Prognoſtics of the Seaſons. As of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as a moiſt Conſtitution of the Year, <hi>South,</hi> or <hi>North</hi> Winds, or Snows are at Hand, you predict thoſe things from the acceſſes of your Pains; and by the abſence of your Pains, you foreknow the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; ſo one way or other, your <hi>Bone-Almanac</hi> ſerves for all Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Lilly</hi>'s and <hi>Gadbury</hi>'s fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>know when it ſhall be Rain-like, or Snow-like, but what Your Honour foreknows, by means of the Gout, does afterwards actually come to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:31629:15"/>paſs. Doctor <hi>Goad</hi> knew more of the Stars, and their Poſitions than you, but not half ſo much of their Influence. <hi>Spinoza</hi> will have it, that when a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Prophet foretold any thing, he gave a Sign, a preſent Sign, which was a confirmation of his Propheſie; you have the Sign within you, Sir, and are a true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet all over.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Majora animalia diutius viſceribus Parentum continentur,</hi> ſays <hi>Pliny.</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture gives to larger ſiz'd Animals a longer ſtay in the Womb of their Mother; their mighty Limbs, and vaſt Frame of Body, are not ſo ſoon faſhion'd and perfected, as is the Compendious texture of leſſer Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals: So is it with the moſt Noble Arts and Sciences, with the moſt uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Inventions, when firſt brought to light; every Man is taken up with unactive Extaſie, and lazy Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, greatly pleas'd to be Taught, and let into Myſtery, and as well content to know no more than is taught him; time paſſes ſilently on,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:31629:16"/>and Ages ſteal away, before there ſtarts up a ſtudious inquiſitive Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who bends his Wit to improve the diſcoveries of his Anceſtors, and raiſe them to their juſt Perfection.</p>
            <p>Now of this Obſervation, I am of the Mind, there is not again in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo clean an Inſtance as the Gout affords us. The Gout, at firſt, paſs'd for no other but an Evil Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which an Exorciſing Prieſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack'd with Charms before ever the Phyſician fell foul upon him with Poiſonous Recipe's. The Phyſician, purely to force a Trade, impos'd upon the People, That the Gout was a Diſeaſe; having cheated them with this falſe Opinion, he plagu'd them with real Tortures, all which he was pleas'd to Chriſten by the general Name of <hi>Therapeutic Method,</hi> in which his barbarous Executions thus follow one another. Firſt <hi>Phle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>botomy,</hi> then <hi>Catharties, Emeties, Hypnotics,</hi> the — and all; and while the inſide of the Poor Patient is thus miſerably Rack'd and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:31629:16"/>he dawbs the outſide with Anodyne Applications, Unguents, and Cataplaſms; and when all is done, I'll give them my Body to Practiſe on, [tho' I had rather the Executioner had it to diſpatch out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right] if plain Cathartic-Gruel, and the Cataplaſm of a freſh Cow-turd do not work greater wonders, than any thing they can pretend to. From <hi>Germany,</hi> nay, from beyond the <hi>Alps,</hi> they come, with hard Names, Exotic Cant, and Baneful Poiſon, to allay the Paroxyſm, and remove the <hi>Procatarxis</hi> of the Gout; but, God be thanked, their Practice de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cays, and muſt do more and more every day, now that it is ſo plainly diſcover'd, that the Gout needs no Remedy, not being, in truth and proper ſpeaking, a Diſeaſe, but a Soveraign Antidote againſt the moſt dangerous Diſeaſes; and therefore People of the beſt ſenſe are content to let it take its courſe, and not only ſo, but they are proud to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the Satisfaction they take, in one
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:31629:17"/>or other advantage, which the Gout affords them. For Inſtance, as to the Fore-knowledge of Weather: The Gout never twitches their Nerves, but they will be telling o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers what changes are towards. Now, that which I propoſe is this, That People ſhould not think it enough to know thus much of the Gout, but ſtudy to improve, and increaſe their knowledge; for, no doubt, more may be made of this Bleſſing, than ever yet was done by the happy Man that has enjoy'd it longeſt. I am perſuaded, that if the fortunate Patient would be at the pains to obſerve all the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Gout, in his pinching, ſmarting, gawling Acceſſes; in his gnawing, ſtabbing, burning Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roxyſms, in his evacuting, tender, remitting Receſſes, he might quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come to wind a Storm, ſo long before, that in a ſhort time, no Ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners would think their Ship ſafe, but with a Gouty Maſter, nor would any experienc'd Seaman, that want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:31629:17"/>a Ship, offer himſelf to the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, but upon Crutches. Poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly here ſome nice Perſon may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, That 'tis a ſad thing to be a Cripple; I reply, In Lameneſs two things are to be conſider'd, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſightly Gate, and the afflicting Pain. <hi>As to the unſightly Gate;</hi> Set the <hi>Italian</hi> Proverb againſt it;
<q>
                  <l>He knows not <hi>Venus</hi> in her perfect ſweetneſs,</l>
                  <l>Who has never lain with a Lame Miſtreſs;</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Montaign</hi> tells us, that the ſame is ſaid of Men, as well as Women; for the Queen of <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zons</hi> anſwer'd the Perſonable <hi>Soy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian,</hi> who courted her to Love, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Lame Men make the beſt Gallants. In that Female Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick, to prevent the Dominion of the Males, they lam'd them Arms and Legs in their Infancy, belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that they would be rather the better, for the uſe which they ſhould make of them thereafter. <hi>Montaign</hi> gives a Philoſophical Reaſon for the advantage accruing by Lameneſs,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:31629:18"/>either to Men or Women, <hi>viz.</hi> The Legs and Thighs not receiving their due Aliment, it falls out, that the Genital Parts above are the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, better ſupplyed, and more vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. 2. <hi>As to the Pain proceeding from Lameneſs.</hi> I will not, to diminiſh that, tell the Objector a long Story from the Reaſonings of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> or the Practice of <hi>Cato;</hi> but only pray him to conſider the lower fort of People, who know little of Example, and mind as little of Precept; Nature is their Guide, and this their fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Practice; they call the Phthiſic, ſays <hi>Montaign,</hi> a Cough; the Bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Flux is no more with them than a Looſneſs; a Pleuriſie, but a ſtitch in the Side; and as they ſoftly Name, ſo they patiently Endure theſe Grievances.</p>
            <p>If the Mercenary Adverſaries of the Gout, the Doctors, have any other Objections againſt a <hi>Bone-Almanac,</hi> beſides what I have anſwer'd, let them be publiſh'd, I will fairly and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:31629:18"/>fully Anſwer them alſo, or renounce my Reverence for the Gout.</p>
            <p>O that I had an infallible Medicine, which would both certainly and ſpeedily cauſe the Gout; [Wine and Women are tedious and uncertain ways of purchaſing the mighty Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,] I would not doubt but to make more of it, than ever <hi>Daffy</hi> did of his <hi>Elixir,</hi> or any ſtroling <hi>Mountebank</hi> of his <hi>Noſtrum.</hi> The Fair for <hi>Rider</hi>'s Almanac, <hi>Partridge</hi>'s Almanac, <hi>Al—ch</hi>'s Almanac, laſts but one Month in the Year; but I might vend <hi>Gout-Almanacs,</hi> and <hi>Bone-Almanacs</hi> all the Year round. Here I ſuſpect that the Malevolent Doctors, that get their Living by their miſchevious Craft in practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing on the Gout, will Object, that all which I have hitherto urg'd in its Commendations, has a very great allay; for tho' it is not Dangerous, yet it is Painful; tho' the Patient has lucid Intervals, yet he has vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Paroxyſms; tho' he be a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, yet the Spirit, which inſpires,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:31629:19"/>rends him. But of theſe Objectors I would fain know, whether Holy preſcious Enthuſiaſm, be not a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ungovernable Impulſe; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lucid Intervals, are not more Eligible than a conſtant, weak, and ſullen Light; whether Pain with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Danger, is not better than Eaſe without Security? I am of Opinion, that our Compoſitions are no more able to endure pure and unmixt Felicities, than <hi>Semele,</hi> the Half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone Mother of <hi>Bacchus,</hi> to abide the the warm Congreſs of the <hi>Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pic Jove,</hi> circled with all his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Yet, to ſilence Envy it ſelf, the next Step we aſcend, we ſhall ſee the Gout dealing to his Patients a Benefit, ſo wondrous, refin'd, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, and uſeful, that he muſt be a very dull Creature, that can ſeriouſly think on this, and not paſſionately wiſh, deliberately conſider it, and not heartily labour, by all honeſt ways, and means to deſerve the Gout.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:31629:19"/>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Gouty Perſons are moſt free from the Head-ach;</hi> the reaſon of which is this.</p>
            <p>— The heavy Recrements of the Blood and Nervous Juyce always fall downward to the Gouty Joynts. The Nerves of the Head, the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres and the Membranes, whereof there are many plac'd above and under the Skull; the two <hi>Meninges,</hi> the Tunicles of the Nerves, the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricranium,</hi> and other <hi>Perioſtia,</hi> the Muſcles, the <hi>Panniculus Carnoſus;</hi> and laſtly, the Skin it ſelf, are all freed from a World of Torment by means of the Medicinal Gout, which attracts, to exteriour remote Parts, vicious Humours of various Deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, and there ſets them on Fire, waſts, and Evacuates them. Perſons, much favour'd by the Gout, upon every long abſence of that beſt Friend of theirs [whether occaſion'd by unknown Accidents, or unwiſe recourſe to the miſchievous tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering of a wicked Doctor] ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change their Freedom from the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:31629:20"/>Gout, for Pain more Intenſe, and Dangerous; but, of all other Pains, they are extremely ſubject to the Head-ach; ſomething of a Cloud, more or leſs, always hang over their Brain: But as ſoon as ever the Gout pleaſes (forgiving their Ingratitude) to Re-viſit them, preſently the Weather breaks up, the Nerves are relax'd, the Fibres unmoleſted, the Membranes and Muſcles recover their right Tone; while the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micous conteſting Particles, thrown off from boiling Blood, and turgid Nervous Juyce, fall down to the remote Parts of the Body; and then the Underſtanding grows clear, the Thoughts brisk and active; and the Patient is fitted, whatever his Station and Employment is in the World, to do the Duty thereof bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than ever. I have been told of ſeveral Sea-Captains [and I have reaſon to believe the Relator] who, during a Fit of the Gout, happening to meet the Enemy, beſtir'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with a vigour that forgot
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:31629:20"/>their Pain, and gave their Order with a ſteddier Preſence of Mind, than ever they were Maſters of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. I have the honour to be known to a Perſon of Quality, who has ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd the Age with ſeveral Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Pieces, who never Publiſh'd a ſorry Trifle, nor ever any thing ſo abſolutely Perfect, Uſeful, and Entertaining, as when he lay under a courſe of the Gout. Then would He Dictate like an Angel, or, which is much the ſame, a Man Inſpired, to his Raviſh'd <hi>Amanuenſis.</hi> That <hi>Amanuenſis</hi> of his, has told me, tho' he lov'd his Maſter very well, yet he was always ſorry for his Recovery; for then his Strength fail'd him, and he was no more than another Writer, I mean a Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Firſt Rate tho'. I know nothing that a Man, when he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joys the Gout, is unfit for, but Jumping, Running of Races, or Foot-ball. The <hi>Amazons,</hi> if they are not belyed, coveted to admit Strangers <hi>Flagrante Paroxiſmo.</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:31629:21"/>Had <hi>Montaign</hi> ever met with the MS. whence I have the Notice, he would have giv'n us a Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Reaſon for it. The Gout be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus beneficial, I bleſs my ſelf to think, that any Patient ſhould be ſo much his own Enemy, as to be weary of it; any Doctor ſo much an Enemy to Mankind, as to offer at the Cure; but Cure it they can't, whatever they pretend, unleſs they Kill the Patient. For my part, I know no difference in the Earth between a Doctor of Phyſic and a Tinker, ſave that the Doctor has more of the Tinker, the Tinker more of the Doctor in him: For, the Tinker effectually Stops that particular Hole which he is hir'd to Stop, tho' he makes two other for't; but the Doctor does but diſturb the Gout which he undertakes to Cure; and when the vicious Humours of the Body are not ſuffer'd to have their courſe to the exteriour remote Parts, there to be ſacrific'd on the <hi>Internodial</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:31629:21"/>Altars of the Gout, they revert with Fury and Indignation, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly Aſſault the Vitals, diffuſe their Venom over all the <hi>Viſcera,</hi> corrupt the Stomach, but more eſpecially affect the Head, with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Pains, which are often fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd by dangerous Swoonings, a <hi>Vertigo,</hi> a failing of Memory; nay, and ſometimes a downright <hi>Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium.</hi> Thus Phyſicians Cure their Patients of the Gout! Then doubly Bleſs'd are the Poor and Needy, who, when they have the Gout, and do not underſtand their own Happineſs, cannot be at the Charge to get rid on't, by a Cure of the Doctors. Nay, beſide the miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous conſequences of their Med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dling, their very Meddling it ſelf, is a ſorer Pain, than the Gout, a thouſand times; ſo that, that Man's Intellectuals muſt not be right, who would not wiſh to have his Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ach Cur'd by the Gout, rather than by the Doctors Methods, <hi>i.e.</hi> by being Purg'd and Blooded, Cupp'd
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:31629:22"/>and Flux'd, Stifled with Spirit of Hartſhorn and Soot, drench'd with Cephalic Juleps, and Waters—Cold as thoſe, that extinguiſh'd the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Heat of that Renowned Thrice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Illuſtrious Heroe, hight Old <hi>Simon</hi> the King. The Gout's a Specific, a Single, Proper, and Effectual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy for the Head-ach; by a ſtrong Revulſion it attracts Morbific Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from the Nobler Parts, and ever while you live, ſay I, keep Pain from your Head, and Sorrow from your Heart. The honeſt Old Beldame made ſport for her Neighbours, when ſhe applyed the Clyſter to her Forehead, the part affected: Again, when her Neighbours turn'd up her Blind-ſide, and play'd the Pipe at her Virgin Avenue, that was a Jeſt to her: Marry Gap, quoth ſhe, 'tis the upper end that akes, and you give Phyſic to the lower; but the Clyſter was a good Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for the Head-ach, tho' planted at diſtance, and ſo the Gout. How neceſſary a Friend to the Head, the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:31629:22"/>Medicinal Gout is, keeping it eaſie, clean, and free from all morbific Matter which diſturbs the Brain, we might partly gueſs, from the ſubtle Obſervation of the Famous <hi>Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius</hi> upon Gonty Perſons, which is communicated to us, by one of the Chaſteſt Hiſtorians among the vera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Emiſſaries, [for the <hi>Chineſe</hi> are bleſs'd with the Gout, as well as the <hi>Europeans;</hi>] It is poſſible, ſaid that wiſe <hi>Mandarin,</hi> for a Lame Gouty Perſon to be a Knave, even in our own Country have I known ſome ſuch; but who ever knew a Gouty Cripple that was a Fool? In a Book of that Great Maſter of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals and Politics, preſented by a <hi>Mandarin</hi> of <hi>Confucius</hi> his own Race, to a Learned Jeſuite who has en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich'd the King of <hi>France</hi>'s Library with it, [but I ſuppoſe the Book was there repoſited, ſince a certain Perſon finiſh'd his Travels,] theſe farther Remarks are delivered, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Fools never acquire the Gout, the Sons of Gouty Perſons are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:31629:23"/>from Dulneſs and Folly by the Sins of their Parents, or if in their Minority their Underſtandings happen to lie a little backward, they ſhall no ſooner enter on their Gouty Inheritance, but a bright Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumination brings the ſame forward: Whatever a Man's natural Powers are, they are ſo improv'd by the Gout, ſo refin'd, ſo heighthned in the Paroxyſm, that I am almoſt tempted to call it a ſort of Natural Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Facile est inventis addere,</hi> what the Noble <hi>Confucius</hi> has ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirably well obſerv'd of the Gout, <hi>viz. That it is a perfect Deletory of Folly,</hi> prompts me to think, that it would be worth inquiry, whether the Gout is not as effectual againſt Madneſs, and we may reaſonably believe that it is ſo, if upon Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation it ſhould be found, that there are no Gouty People in <hi>Bedlam;</hi> and then for the Recovery of thoſe poor Creatures to their Wits again, it will not need much Conſideration, whether they ought not to be excus'd
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:31629:23"/>the hard blows which their barbarous Keepers deal them; and the The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rapeutic Method of Purging, Blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, Cupping, Fluxing, Vomiting, Clyſtering, Juleps, Apozemes, Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Confections, Epithemes, and Cataplaſms, with which the more barbarous Doctors Torment them; and inſtead of all their Learned Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, indulg'd, for a time only, a little Intemperance, as to Wine, or Women, or ſo; or the Scholar's Delight of Feeding worthily, and Sleeping heartily, whereby they might get the Gout, and then their Madneſs were cur'd.</p>
            <p>Many and great are the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages which accrue to Mortal Man from the Gout, as cannot but ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently appear to Your Worſhip, from what I have, in running haſte, obſerv'd; but far more numerous, and unconceivably vaſt are the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements, which a Man, worthy of the Gout, and ſenſible of his Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, might, with attentive Care, and ſedulous Obſervance, make.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:31629:24"/>Yet I ſhall not inſiſt on conjectural Topics to do Juſtice to ſo effectual a Promoter of the Safety of humane Life; but proceed on thoſe Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, which are the Objects of Senſe; ſo that, if there be any Perſon, that ſhall Think, or Speak ill of the Gout, he muſt be one, that does not deſire, or deſerve to Live.</p>
            <p>It is a Lofty Heighth, to which I have advanc'd Your Worſhip; Four ſteep Aſcents you have already climb'd, but the Honour of the Gout, <hi>Caput inter nubila condit.</hi> Can your Head bear to mount a Fifth? But why do I ask that Queſtion? The Gout it ſelf will enable you.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>The Gout preſerves its Patients from the great Danger of Fevers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gouty Perſons, by reaſon of a fixt Dyſcraſy of the Blood, are not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to Fevers, As they live free from the dreadful Pains of the Head-ach, ſo likewiſe, from the ſcorching Heat of Fevers. Every one knows, that a Fever is a high
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:31629:24"/>diſorderly Motion, or over-boiling of the Blood, which ſeldom, or never, happens to Gouty Perſons, becauſe the malignant Recrements of the Blood, and Nervous Juyce, which occaſion Fevers, are continually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſited in the Joynts of Gouty Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, are there impriſon'd, water'd, and conſum'd by the Purging, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, Cleanſing, Sanative Fire of the burning Gout. There is a Natural Motion, and Heat in the Blood, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending partly on its proper <hi>Craſis</hi> and Conſtitution [for being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd of Spirit, Salt, and Sulphur, Principles vigorous and active, it ſpontaneouſly grows Turgid and Tumultuous, like Generous Wine in narrow Veſſel pent,] and partly to the Ferment implanted in the Heart, which Rarifies the Liquor paſſing thorugh its Chancls, and and forces it to riſe with Efferve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence frothy. The Preter-natural Ebullition of the Blood, is caus'd either by ſome Extraneous, Hetero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geneous Mixture, or from the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:31629:25"/>Exaltation of its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Spirit, or Sulphur, which when it happens, preſently a high, and quick Pulſe follows; the Blood, like a Sulphurous Liquor, taking Fire, diffuſes its burning Heat all over the Body.</p>
            <p>The vaſt <hi>Sicilian Chaſms,</hi> which vomit Flaming Heaps of Matter, Sulphurous, and Combuſtible, what are they, but Nature's Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemes of a burning fiery Fever? And when the Poets Fable, That haughty <hi>Typhocus,</hi> big <hi>Eryx,</hi> and bold <hi>Enceladus,</hi> deep buryed in the Earth by angry <hi>Jupiter,</hi> belch out thoſe Fires, which waſte the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and fright the Inhabitants, what mean'd they to denote, but the Reſtleſneſs of ſtrenuous Heroes [for want of the Gout to withdraw the Feveriſh Fuel] frying in Flames Mercileſs, and Deſtructive?</p>
            <p>Methinks I pity the Young, and Healthy, whoſe Blood flows tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately, and never knew diſorder; I pity them, I ſay, not for their
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:31629:25"/>preſent Eaſe, but becauſe of their imminent Danger. For when a Royal Sun of <hi>France</hi> blazes, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes in Flames Painted by a brave <hi>Ruſſel</hi>'s Maſterly Hand; when a vanquiſh'd Admiral ſhifts off in Boat Inglorious, a King of equal Valour from a ſafe Station all the while be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the <hi>Monſieur</hi>'s prudent care to preſerve a Great Commander; when a haughty <hi>Mareſchal</hi> is beat out of the Strongeſt Bulwark, that Fenc'd his Maſter's treacherous Rapine, and, to induce that Maſter of his for once to keep the Cartel, can, in ſpight of all his bluſtering, part with his Sword: When Rebel Invaders are diſappointed, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable Aſſaſſines puniſh'd, at ſuch tempting occaſions as theſe, who can forbear a rightful, lawful, and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Glaſs? Yet on ſo ſolemn a Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, if the Healthy gives Nature but a Fillip, it may perchance throw him into a Fever, and that Fever perchance coſt him his Life; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Man that's obnoxious to the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:31629:26"/>Gout, chearfully ventures the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Day, well-knowing, that when the worſt comes to the worſt, 'tis but roaring in Purgatory ſome Forty Days, or ſo; and by that time the Gout has waſted, and cleans'd off the Tartarous Recrements of undigeſted <hi>Falern,</hi> who knows but good News may come to make another Holy-day.</p>
            <p>Purgatory, which cleanſes the Souls of the departed from their Filth, which ſets them out of the Danger of the Lake, and renders them (like burnt Tobacco-pipes) clean and pure, and fit for Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, is a true Picture of the Fire of the Gout, which ſpends the Morbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſic Matter, that might otherwiſe throw the Body into a Helliſh Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Indeed, <hi>Infidels</hi> and <hi>Heretics</hi> may object, and ſay, that perhaps Purgatory is but a falſe Story, but no matter for that; for Grave Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors teach, that a falſe Story may be a true Picture, and ſerve to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate as neceſſary a Doctrin as that
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:31629:26"/>of Purgatory, but in this, I am po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive, that neither a falſe Story, nor a true one, can illuſtrate a more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Maxim than this, That the Purging Fires of the Gout withdraw the Fuel, from the deſtructive Fires of burning Fevers.</p>
            <p>Thoſe learned and worthy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, that write of Devils and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and know the Natures and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of them as perfectly, as heart can wiſh, tell us, that there be two ſorts of them, <hi>White</hi> and <hi>Black, Good</hi> and <hi>Bad:</hi> So is it certainly with Diſeaſes; the Gout, if it be lawful to call it a Diſeaſe, is a good and uſeful Diſeaſe, a <hi>White</hi> Devil; the Fever, a bad and hurtful Diſeaſe, a <hi>Black</hi> Devil, the Devil of a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, or a Diſeaſe that is the Devil, whom if ever the Phyſician caſts out, I'll Swear it is by Compact: Whereas the Gout is an honeſt Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brifuge, the Operations thereof Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, and Intelligible, ſomething Painful indeed, but there's no Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gic
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:31629:27"/>in them. By the way, If the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician cures or caſts out <hi>Black</hi> Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes or Devils, by Compact with <hi>Black</hi> Devils, may it not be ſaid to be a double wickedneſs? For I took it to be the <hi>Roman</hi> Prieſt's ungodly Office, with rumbling Exorciſms to eject them; but this is the fault alſo of other Dealers, there's nothing more common among them than to encroach upon one another's Trade. Could Tyrants inflict Fevers, they would never make uſe of Rack or Gibbet, Axe, or unrighteous Judge, unleſs the object of their Fate were an honeſt Gouty Fellow; for the Gout would ſoften the feveriſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, as the Popiſh Printer did his Father Confeſſor's Pennance, when he boil'd the Peaſe, which he was requir'd to put in his Shoes before he took his walk. There is not certainly a ſevere Torment than a Burning Fever, nor a more Sovereign Antidote than the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinal Gout; ſo that 'tis a Truth,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:31629:27"/>clear as the Sun, if more People had the Gout, fewer would die of a Fever. Having plac'd theſe things in ſo clear a light, I am ſtrongly perſuaded, that not Your Worſhip only, but the generality of the Age will ſet their prejudices aſide, and yield to the happy force of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny uſeful Truths, which, by the bright Illumination of a violent Gout-Paroxyſm, I have here diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd; ſo that hereafter, inſtead of the Old parting Complements, — <hi>Save you, Sir, God keep you in good Health,</hi> I queſtion not but we ſhall ſay, — <hi>The Gout defend you, Sir, God give you the Gout;</hi> for we ought not to hope for a Bleſſing without the means. To wiſh a Man the Gout, is to wiſh him that, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draws Fuel from Diſeaſes, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves Life at ſo cheap a rate, it coſts a Man not a Penny more than Patience.</p>
            <p>It has been the Opinion of ſome Writers, that none can be ſav'd,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:31629:28"/>who die of the Plague, but in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Future State of others, I think it beſt to venture being mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken on the Charitable ſide; and therefore I wou'd ſooner believe, that none can be Damn'd who have the Gout; and I muſt tell Your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that I have known a leſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable Sign of Salvation giv'n by a Diſſenting <hi>Rabbi</hi> to his Hearers.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Mercury,</hi> by the mighty Power of a Verſe, borrow'd from that great Architect <hi>Homer,</hi> heav'd up the aſpiring Mountain <hi>Pelion,</hi> and pil'd it intire on Heav'n-ſhouldring <hi>Oſſa,</hi> and then help'd <hi>Charon</hi> up to the top; the poor old Ferry-man complain'd, That the diſtance from the Earth was ſo great, that he could not ſee what was done there: I am much afraid, Sir, that this up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt Step of Aſcent, on which I am going to Seat Your Worſhip, that you may have a full view of the amazing Excellence of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinal, Uſeful, Health-reſtoring,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:31629:28"/>Soul-enliv'ning Gout, will place you at ſuch a vaſt diſtance above Terrene Things and Notions, that you will not be able to diſcern the true proportion of that Benefit which Crowns the Honour of the Gout; at leaſt, not ſo plainly as I could wiſh.</p>
            <p n="6">6. To Crown the Honour of the Gout, <hi>It is not to be Cur'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Gout defies all your Groſs Galenical Methods, and all your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted Chymical Preparations; for, the conjunct Cauſes thereof (as the Learned <hi>Willis</hi> confeſſes) lie in parts ſo very remote, that the Virtues of no Medicines can reach them; and Heaven be praiſed for it, for why, Sir, would you <hi>Cure</hi> [as you call it] the Gout, which gives you Pain without Danger, a better taſte of Health by an acquaintance with Pain, a knowledge of future things, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from the Head-ach, and from Fevers?</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:31629:29"/>
            <p>Bleſs us! That any Man ſhould wiſh to be rid of the Gout, for want of which he may become obnoxious to Fevers, and Head-ach, be blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in his Underſtanding, loſe the taſte of his Health, and the ſecurity of his Life. I hope you and I, dear Sir, ſhall be better advis'd, and to ſhew that we are ſo, and at the ſame time, to ſet the World a good Example, I hope we ſhall neither of us ever tamper with the Doctor for the Cure of the Gout, which really and truly is incurable, unleſs the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent be to be kill'd; which is what the Doctor's Medicines aim at, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not what He directly aims at himſelf: For his Heart is chiefly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Fee; his Prayers, that his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient may neither Die, nor Recover; at leaſt not Die, while he's worth a Penny; but when his laſt Penny is ſpent, then the miſerable Creature is forſaken, like the Poor Woman in the Goſpel, and may Periſh for all him, unleſs Heav'n has a Miracle
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:31629:29"/>in ſtore for a Poor Sinner that has been tormented by a naſty D— before his time. But leſt I ſhould be thought, in vindication of the Honour of the Gout, too ſevere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Pretenders to Cure it, I ſhall argue againſt them, from their own confeſſions: We may ſay of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Medicaſter, whether a College, or a Stage-Doctor, <hi>habemus confiten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem reum;</hi> the whole Clan of them are Homicides by their own Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Other wicked People put on the Guiſe of honeſty, for the better perpetrating their Crimes; but Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians own the Roguery of their Art; indeed, to ſave themſelves from public Infamy, they give this ſoftning turn to their ſcandalous Cauſe. The Principles of their Art, they ſay, are difficult to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and uncertain to be relied on; and then alſo the temperament of the Body, on which they Practice, can be but gueſs'd at; ſo that, the ſucceſs of the moſt Learned Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:31629:30"/>can be but caſual. Now, that after this, theſe Men ſhould be entertain'd, and ſo general admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance giv'n to their Practice, does evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently prove, that the generality of Men, when they loſe their Health, loſe their Wits together with it. I will allow, that it were reaſonable for a Sick Man liberally to part with his Guinea's for his Health, if the Doctors, that have their Money in Hand, were ſure of reſtoring Health, or upon failure would refund; but to pay down ready Money for a Lot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery-Chance, where 'tis great odds but the Adventurer encreaſes his Malady, and haſtens his Death! I, for my part, declare againſt it, and am perſuaded, that no one who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders rightly, but would keep his Money and bear his Burthen. A ſpare and eaſie Diet ſhall be always my Phyſic, and I will leave it to Nature to do her own work. But let us come to ſome more particular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments of theſe deadly Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Mankind.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:31629:30"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Galen,</hi> that is ſtill rever'd as a God by Modern Practitioners, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges it impoſſible to find out a Medicine that ſhall do any great good one way, and not do as much hurt another. The Learned Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> fatally experienc'd the truth of this acknowledgment; the Medicine which was preſcrib'd him to Cure the Gout, mov'd the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel from his Kidneys, which being too big to paſs the Ureters, choak'd the Channel, and depriv'd him of his Life that way. <hi>Cornelius Agrippa</hi> tells us of one <hi>Rafis,</hi> a Phyſician of Note, who conſidering the fooliſh credulity of Patients, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious ignorance of Profeſſors in Phyſic, adviſed that never above one Doctor ſhould be made uſe of at a time; giving this reaſon, Becauſe the miſtake of a ſingle Man was leſs dangerous: And I would adviſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to uſe any; for, as the miſtake of one Man is leſs dangerous than of a Conſult of them, ſo the having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:31629:31"/>to do with any one, is leſs dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous than the miſtake of one; for Nature can commit no miſtake, but if not loaded with Luxury, nor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd with Phyſic, will vigorouſly ſtrive to throw off every noxious Diſeaſe. Such the Gout is not, for Nature throwing off Morbific Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the remoter parts of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, does deſignedly beget the Gout, and make uſe of that admirable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, to Cure Diſeaſes already got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and to prevent others. But it is not meer reaſon which I rely upon, when I adviſe Men to truſt Nature alone for their Recovery, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver go to a Phyſician, I have the greateſt Authority to ſupport my advice. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.12. <hi>Aſa</hi> in the 39th. Year of his Reign was diſeas'd in his Feet [as I am now, which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders me from running to my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentators] but I remember the Phraſe of the Septuagint, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, his Feet were ſoft and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der [ſwell'd with the Gout, that
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:31629:31"/>muſt be the meaning] until his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe [Gout] was exceeding great, yet in his Diſeaſe [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the extreme ſoftneſs and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Gout] he ſought not to the Lord, but to the Phyſician. I do not ſee how our Doctors of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick can evade the force of this Text, in defence of their Profeſſion; for 'tis a very weak and precarious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, which they make, when they tell us, That <hi>Aſa</hi> is blam'd, not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly for ſeeking to the Phyſicians, but for not truſting in the Lord, when he ſought to them. Now I will grant theſe Gentlemen, that it is the duty of Patients, to truſt in the Lord, when they ſeek to the Phyſicians; nay, it is their Duty to truſt in the Lord, then, above any other time; for then they run themſelves into thoſe hazards, that, if the Lord does not help them, 'tis odds but they miſcarry. But I would have theſe Phyſicians, who make but ſorry In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters of Scripture, to conſider,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:31629:32"/>that the Text ſets ſeeking the Lord, and ſeeking the Phyſician, in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to one another; plainly enough implying, that the former was his Duty, the latter his Fault. But our Phyſicians, it ſeems, would have the Sick ſeek to the Lord, and them both; as if the Lord could not do his own work without them. <hi>Odi profanum Genus.</hi> — Hence, Sir, it is plain to me, that they are an Order of Men that Care not much what they ſay or do, to uphold their own Honour, and keep their ungodly Trade a going: But therefore I would wiſh all unhealthy People, who have bought their Miſery of the Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors; and all honeſt Gentlemen, who are preſerv'd by the Salutary Gout in the Land of the Living, to prefer a Bill in Parliament againſt this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Order of Men, that by a ſtrong <hi>Cathartic</hi> Act, they may be Purg'd out of His Majeſty's Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; I will engage that there's never a Family in the Nation, but
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:31629:32"/>ſhall by this means, beſides their Health, ſave their Taxes, ſo that a vigorous War may be continued againſt <hi>France,</hi> till the <hi>Monſieur</hi>'s not worth a Livre, and no body with us ever the Poorer. For ſuch an uſeful Decree, we are not without a Preſident in Hiſtory. The Wiſe <hi>Romans,</hi> under <hi>Marcus Porcius Cato,</hi> Baniſh'd Phyſicians, not only from <hi>Rome,</hi> but alſo from <hi>Italy,</hi> which Council, it may be reaſonably thought, contributed not a little to the increaſe of their People; for, as where the moſt Lawyers are, there are the moſt Quarrels and Contentions; ſo where the moſt Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, there the moſt Funerals; and ſome ſay, where the moſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, there the moſt differences about Religion; but that's not the fault of the Divines; for if the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate would let the ſtrongeſt Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty alone, they would force all the reſt to be of their Opinion. But I am afraid I forget my ſelf in too
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:31629:33"/>long a Digreſſion; what I ought chiefly to inſiſt on, is, the Superla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Excellence of the Gout, which is never to be remov'd. The fear of loſing a Bleſſing takes off from the pleaſure of enjoying it. Thieves may plunder your Houſe, Age will ruine your Beauty, Envy may aſperſe your Reputation, Bribes corrupt your Faith, but the Gout is a ſure Inheritance; neither Thieves, nor Knaves; neither Time, nor Envy, nor any thing elſe, can deſpoil you of it. A Man may, himſelf, if he has a mind to't, ſquander his Eſtate, blemiſh his comely Form, injure his Fame, and renounce his Honeſty; but let him get rid of the Gout if he can; that bleſſing he may take Comfort in, being ſecure, that 'tis for his Life. They ſay, there's more Care and Trouble in keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Eſtate, than getting it; as for the Gout, there may be ſome trouble in getting it, tho' that is mixt with pleaſure too, but no Man
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:31629:33"/>is put to the leaſt care or trouble for the ſafe keeping of the Gout; he may endure Miſery enough indeed, if he ſeeks to the Phyſician for the Cure of it. You cannot be always Young and Handſom; but Gouty once, and Gouty ever; thence came the Proverb, <hi>Drink Claret, and have the Gout; and Drink no Claret, and ſtill have it:</hi> The Gout, 'tis true, is the Reward of ſome Works, but there's no forfeiting it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in 'tis preferable to a Crown Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial. Poſſibly a Wiſe and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Perſon may ſecure his Virtue again dangerous Temptations, but then he muſt be always upon his Guard; but let him take as little Care of himſelf as he pleaſes, he ſhall never have the leſs Gout for his looſe way of Living. But poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly it may be objected, That the Gout, Curing other Diſeaſes, and not being to be Cur'd it ſelf, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes an encouragement to Intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, and Luſt. The Luſtful,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:31629:34"/>and In temperate Drink, and Love on, reckoning that the Gout will carry off the Evil Conſequences of wild Exceſs, and fooliſh Paſſion. Now I will not lye for the Gout, as much as I Honour it: If it were not for this one — abatement, 'twere Phyſic for an Angel. But, that the Reader may not reproach me for a groſs Philoſophical Error, I declare, that I do not mean, <hi>for the Spiritual Subſtance of an Angel,</hi> for that, I well know, needs no Phyſic, of one ſort, or other; but for the Corporeal Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hicle which an Angel may chance to aſſume; which Vehicle, being rectified by the Gout, may, with leſs trouble, be actuated by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel.</p>
            <p>Sir, I thought to have taken a longer View of the Excellency of the Noble Gout, from this ſublime Aſcent, which repreſents it with its greateſt advantage, the advantage of being Incurable: But, alas! the violent Paroxyſm, which I have la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour'd
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:31629:34"/>under for theſe three ſhort Days and Nights, abates; the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſeneſs of my Pains conſiderably remits, and therefore I am forc'd to break off abruptly; for I am ſenſible, that no Man can do Honour to the Gout by a juſt and adequate Pane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gvric, but he that at the time of Writing feels it in extremity.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:31629:35"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31629:35"/>
            <head>To all the numerous Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of <hi>Apollo,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Dogmatical</hi> Sons of Art, or <hi>Empirical</hi> By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blows.</head>
            <head type="sub">To all <hi>Pharmaceutic</hi> Reſidentia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in Town, or City; alſo to all Stroling Practitioners and Impoſtors.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF this Letter ſhall happen in any meaſure to ſpoil your Trade, Heaven make me thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; for, well I know, that yours is the very Trade, of two Famous Princes, that have by one Method
<pb facs="tcp:31629:36"/>or other, ridd out of the way, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great numbers of Men.</p>
            <p>A Malefactor Condemn'd to Die, ought to be free from all manner of inſults as he goes to Execution. I know it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do not Dedicate this Letter to you, by way of Inſult, but Friendly to mind you, that ſince your unrighteous Trade is Broke, or Breaking, You would timely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think your ſelves, what Honeſt Employment you may be fit for; If you'll take my advice, you ſhall Travel; for, to your Sorrow, you have known an over-grown <hi>Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier</hi> from abroad, make a great <hi>Doctor</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> Why ſhould not you make as good <hi>Farriers</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, as they do <hi>Doctors</hi> here? This is certain, like true <hi>Farriers,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:31629:36"/>you have Preſcrib'd to many a weak Man a Medicine for a Horſe; ſo then, for the <hi>Materia Medica</hi> 'tis the ſame, nothing will be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſom, and uneaſie to you; in your New Profeſſion, but that you ſhall never get as much by Practiſing on the Spavin, as the Gout; but you muſt be content with leſs Earnings; What! you can't in Conſcience expect as much for Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a Horſe, as a Man.</p>
            <p>To this Change of your Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, not only the diſcovery of the Frands and Dangers thereof, but alſo the Name of your Great Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron <hi>Hippocrates</hi> invites — What are You more than He? Come, come, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Change Name and Profeſſion, better a Murrain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb facs="tcp:31629:37"/>Horſes than a Plague among Men.</p>
            <p>Having thus oblig'd you, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, in an <hi>Epiſtle Decicatory,</hi> by minding you of the imminent Decay of your Practice upon Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Bodies, and teaching you how to make the beſt of a bad Market, by trying experiments up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Horſe-fleſh; I hope you will make me that grateful return, as to prevent the Obligation I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer on you from turning to my prejudice; therefore if any Gouty Perſon that may happen to malign you, ſhall object againſt me, and ſay, I had better have made a Forlorn Regiment of you, and ſent you to have been knock'd o'th' head in <hi>Flanders,</hi> than given you a Licence to Kill Horſes,
<pb facs="tcp:31629:37"/>remember to ſay this for your Selves and your Benefactor, <hi>That when the Devils were ejected out of Humane Bodies, they were ſuffer'd to enter into Swine.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
